A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Division, Program Area One FA572
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, International Division, Program Area One
Bulk, 1962-1968 1953-1970
1962-1968
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA572
2.4 Cubic Feet
The collection was created by combining inactive records from various staff members within the International Division. The records span various decades from 1953 to 1970. The collection consists of Field Office Files and portions of the subject files of two Foundation staff members, Herbert Passin and Melvin Fox. The Field Office files hold correspondence, memoranda and reports originating from the Latin America and Caribbean (LAC) and South and Southeast Asia (SSEA) regional offices. Melvin Fox's subject files primarily pertain to the Language Development Study (1966-1967). Herbert Passin's subject files document his work as a consultant, focusing on education and cooperation between the United States and Japan, including basic dockets on the Foundation's Japan program (1963-1966) and support for English as a Second Language (1966).
(6 Hollinger document boxes)
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Separated Materials note
Appendix A: Reports – Unpublished reports written by Ford Foundation staff and consultants were removed from their original folders, scanned and transferred to the Archives' collection of staff and consultant reports. See Appendix A for a list of these reports and their specific assigned number. The reports are listed in alphabetical order by author. The assigned number may be used to access reports in the online catalog.
Biographical/Historical note
The Ford Foundation has been engaged in overseas work since the early 1950s. The Foundation's aspiration to become a national and international philanthropy for the advancement of human welfare was first formally expressed in the seminal 1949 report of the Gaither Study Committee, which was commissioned by the Board of Trustees to chart the future. In 1951, the Foundation established two of its first grant programs, Overseas Development (OD) and Overseas Training and Research (OTR). The granting goals were to increase agricultural production, improve health and living conditions, and advance education. South and Southeast Asia were the initial focus, with India and Pakistan receiving the majority of grants. A more limited number of grants were issued in Indonesia and Burma. A program for smaller regional and national grants also was initiated for the Near East. In 1957, Overseas Development further expanded to include programs in Latin America.
In 1957, the Foundation established a program in International Training and Research (ITR) the goal of which was to strengthen American competence in foreign affairs and international relations. ITR supported scholarship and teaching in areas where American knowledge and trained personnel were limited. The Foundation offered area studies in Asia, Africa, the Near East, the Soviet Union, and East Europe. In its international training and exchange programs, the Foundation and its grantees coordinated closely with the U.S. State Department, which sponsored exchanges between the United States and other countries as a matter of government policy.
During the first couple decades of the Foundation's existence the differentiation between program areas had yet to be established. According to the 1949 Gaithner Report that laid the groundwork for the Ford Foundation's work as an international philanthropy, the goal of Program Area One was the Establishment of Peace. This program had four parts: the mitigation of world tensions, the development of the understanding and conditions for peace among peoples of the world, the strengthening of the United Nations, and the improvement of both private and public American participation in world affairs. Much of the work of the Overseas Development Program therefore fell under the auspices of Program Area One.
As part of a Foundation reorganization in 1966, the Overseas Development Program, along with other international programs such as International Training and Research (ITR) and Population, became part of a single International Division (ID). A subsequent restructuring of the International Division occurred in 1980-1981 and led to the creation of the Developing Countries Program (DCP). DCP was again restructured in 1989, resulting in the separating of programs in Africa and the Middle East (AME, formerly MEA), Asia (ASIA), Latin American and the Caribbean (LAC/OLAC), Human Rights and Governance (HRG), Education and Culture (EC), Program-Related Investments (PRI), and International Affairs (IA) as independent program areas.
Biographical/Historical note
Melvin J. Fox was born on November 26, 1913 and graduated from American University in 1940 with a B.A. in International Economics. He joined the Ford Foundation in July 1951 as a consultant on international affairs and served as part of its charter staff. In November of the same year he became a staff associate and, in 1953, he advanced to Executive Associate for International Training and Research (ITR). Mr. Fox was promoted to Program Associate in October of 1957 and he served as Associate Director of the International Training and Research Program from 1961 through 1966. In early 1967, he became Program Officer for Planning and Evaluation in the International Division, and later that year was promoted to Deputy Representative for West Africa within the Middle East and Africa (MEA) Program. Mr. Fox subsequently held the positions of Program Officer for the Middle East and Africa (1970) and Program Advisor for MEA (1972) before rising to Representative for West Africa in May 1975. From September 5 to November 2, 1983, he became Acting Representative for the Developing Countries Program in Lagos, Nigeria. During his time at Ford, his work focused on foreign academic exchange, the teaching of the English language abroad, development projects in Africa, and African studies at U.S. Universities. Mr. Fox died in 1998.
Herbert Passin was born in Chicago on December 16, 1916 and graduated from the University of Illinois with a B.A. in Genetics. Later, in 1941, he received a B.A. and a M.A. in Anthropology from Northwestern University.
When World War II broke out, Mr. Passin learned Japanese at an army language school, and in December 1945, served as chief of the Public Opinion and Sociological Research Division in General MacArthur's headquarters in Tokyo. He later held positions at the University of California, the Social Science Research Council in Japan, Ohio State University, the Congress of Cultural Freedom, the University of Washington in Seattle, and Columbia University in New York.
The Ford Foundation hired Mr. Passin as a consultant for his expertise on Japan in 1962. He served as a program advisor during the Foundation's expansion into Japan. In 1967, Mr. Passin helped found the Shimoda Conference and the first U.S.-Japan parliamentary exchange program. He returned to Columbia University, where he chaired the Sociology Department from 1973 to 1977. He died on February 26, 2003 at the age of 86.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged into 3 series.
Scope and Contents note
The International Division Program Area One Files are an artificially created collection of records from the International Division (ID) and International Training and Research (ITR) spanning from 1953 to 1970. The collection consists of Field Office Files and portions of the subject files of two staff members, Herbert Passin and Melvin Fox.
The Field Office Files contain correspondence, memoranda and reports originating from the Latin America and Caribbean (LAC) and South and Southeast Asia (SSEA) regional offices. The correspondence in the field office files relates to then-ongoing programs, such as the Foundation's support for the distribution of inter-uterine devices for birth control in India (1965-1966). Internal memoranda describe policy issues, from cost of living expenses for Foundation staff and local litigation over housing in Pakistan to Foundation policy on travel and study awards. Reports include one on a Foundation mission to Mexico (1964) and an economic and development report on India (1964). The subject files of Melvin Fox contained in this collection primarily pertain to a Language Development Study (1966-1967). The study researched the best method for teaching languages, particularly foreign or second languages. The correspondence associated with the study reveals some of the academic disputes over the findings.
Herbert Passin, an expert on Japan who served as a program advisor for the Foundation's expansion into Asia, is one of the few consultants whose files have been retained. His subject files focus on education and cooperation between the United States and Japan, including basic dockets on the Foundation's Japan program (1963-1966) and support for English as a Second Language (1966).
Related Archival Materials note
FA548 Ford Foundation records, International Affairs Division, Program Staff Files, 1956-1990. This collection documents various periods of the Foundation's overseas programs between 1956 and 1990. It includes additional office files of Melvin Fox.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Biographical / Historical
Segment One: International Activities of the Ford Foundation: An Overview
The Foundation's aspiration to become a national and international philanthropy for the advancement of human welfare was first formally expressed in the seminal 1949 report of the Gaither Study Committee, Report of the Study for the Ford Foundation on Policy and Program (RAC Library, call letters 361.7 GAI ), which was commissioned by the Board of Trustees to chart the Foundation's future. Foundation Trustees launched Ford's international grantmaking activities in 1950 when they approved the committee's report and its embrace of peace, democracy, and freedom. Since then, the Foundation has tackled these goals using a variety of strategies and responding to changing contexts, from the Cold War to the 1989 fall of the Berlin Wall and beyond.
Toward the Foundation's aspiration‎al goal, "the establishment of peace", its international activities have comprised a wide range of conceptual approaches and focus areas. These include international affairs, international studies, international understanding, arms control and disarmament, international law, international economic concerns, and overseas development in nearly every region of the world. Three distinct periods emerge for the international grantmaking defined by external contextual changes and internal changes in Foundation leadership and structures: the expansion era of 1950-1965; the transition and restructuring years of 1966-1988; and the post-1989 shift away from Cold War dichotomies. During each of the distinct historical periods the consistent objectives were: 1) to ensure freedom and democracy in developed countries; 2) to foster education and international understanding in all countries; and 3) to contribute to the social, economic, and political development of less developed countries.
Biographical / Historical
Segment 2. Period Sketch - The Expansion Era 1950-1965
The Ford Foundation's expansion era (1950-1965) began when the Gaither Study Committee Report placed "peace" as the area of top priority for the Foundation and set the Ford Foundation on a global course. Board Chair Henry Ford II writing in the 1951 Annual Report of the Foundation, identified "the danger of war" as the "the prime threat to human welfare today." Under the leadership of the three Ford Foundation presidents in this period-- Paul Hoffman, H. Rowan Gaither and Henry Heald--and several key trustees, notably the two seriatim chairs, John J. McCloy and Julius A. Stratton, the Foundation programs were largely informed by the post-World War II desire to avoid nuclear war and promote greater understanding among the world's peoples, strengthening of the United Nations, and enhancing both private and public American participation in world affairs. The strong board presence of university presidents and former leaders of postwar reconstruction efforts in Europe also helped to inform Ford's approach to building the field of peace and international security in the United States and encouraged extensive overseas activities.
For example, the first three presidents of the expanded Foundation ranged from government and business leadership experience to academic and nonprofit: Paul Hoffman (at Ford, 1950-1953) ran the Marshall Plan in Europe; H. Rowan Gaither Staffer (1948-1953), President (1953-1956) and Trustee (1956-1958) had MIT and Rand experience; Henry Heald, former president, Illinois Institute of Technology and New York University, President (1956-1966). The trustees also ran the leadership gamut from government and nonprofits to academic: Trustee John J. McCloy (from 1953; chair, 1959-1965) was assistant Secretary of War during World War II and chairman of the Council on Foreign Relations; and Trustee Julius A. Stratton (Trustee from 1955; chair, 1966-1970) was president of MIT.
When Ford became an international foundation in 1950, it had a small staff and operated through separate funds. The expansive period in the 1950s and 1960s resulted in a large number of field offices, which increased Ford's global footprint. Support focused on a mix of US university-based programs for research and training; think-tanks for policy-oriented meetings and policy research; and action projects specifically in less developed countries. The Foundation's focus on peace, freedom, and democracy played out against the Cold War backdrop for scientific and military competition between the United States, the Soviet Union and China.
Under President Hoffman, the Foundation's work was organized by the areas identified in the Gaither Committee Report: Area One, the Establishment of Peace; Area Two, The Strengthening of Democracy; Area Three, The Strengthening of the Economy; Area Four, Education in a Democratic Society; and Area Five, Individual Behavior and Human Relations.
Program differentiation began in the Gaither era. When he began in 1953, he introduced the following programs, with international work under nearly all of them: International Programs, Public Affairs Programs, Program in Economic Development and Administration [mainly U.S. based], Education Program, The TV-Radio Workshop, and Behavioral Sciences Program. In 1954, the Foundation gave prominence to the international work explicitly through changing the program names and separating international affairs and overseas development. The 1954 program names were: The Advancement of Education, Education for Democracy, Increasing Knowledge of Foreign Areas, Economic Development and Administration, the Behavioral Sciences, and Overseas Development. In 1955, Increasing Knowledge of Foreign Areas became Increasing International Understanding. In 1956, the last year of the Gaither presidency, the program roster read: Education in the United States, The Behavioral Sciences, Public Affairs, Hospital Aid (only in the U.S.), Economic Development and Administration, International Understanding, and Overseas Development. Names changed but the program focus often remained the same.
President Heald maintained the areas of international interest of Hoffman and Gaither. The International Affairs program housed the programs based in the United States, Europe and Japan, with a few activities linking American and developing countries institutions. The Overseas Training and Research Program took over the efforts to increase American understanding of international issues. From 1957-1959, an International Legal Studies program, run from New York, helped build law programs in developing countries. Starting in 1959, the Overseas Development program comprised all the regional and country offices. In fiscal year 1964, Heald convinced the trustees to add a new focus on population, with grants both in the United States and overseas.
Biographical / Historical
Segment 2. Period Summary - The Expansion Era 1950-1965
With the ever-increasing budget and trustee willingness to invade capital, presidents Hoffman, Gaither and Heald oversaw vast growth in the Foundation's international activities in the United States, other developed countries and developing countries. Activities crossed disciplines, institutions, and national boundaries, although few crossed intra-foundation boundaries. Under the three presidents, Foundation staff in various domestic and international offices from New York interacted with the regional and country offices headed by representatives. Usually in this period, however, these offices in fact worked more closely with local governments than with New York staff, reinforcing the commitment to locally led social and economic development in less-developed countries.
The shared values of this early period reflected as much the continuing competition between the Communist and capitalist worlds as the concerns about maintaining peace. The Cold War provided the contextual continuity for grantmaking on the core themes of increasing American understanding of the rest of the world, building and strengthening connections not only with European and Asian democracies but also with Eastern European countries, the Soviet Union, China, and Cuba.
Biographical / Historical
Segment 3. Period Sketch - Transition and Restructuring 1966-1988
In the 1960s, the Ford Foundation Trustees began to rethink the role of the Foundation in the context of the era's dramatic political and cultural changes. For instance, the passage of the 1964 Civil Rights Act created a domestic policy context in which the Foundation could more deeply engage with issues of rights and social justice. Events overseas starting in the late 1960s would extend the rights agenda to international affairs and development operations at the Foundation -- all advanced by the leadership of McGeorge Bundy (president, 1966-1979).
McGeorge Bundy was appointed president in 1966, following a significant career in national security and academic administration. During World War II, he worked with the Army's intelligence division, and in the early post-war years was a political analyst at the Council on Foreign Relations. Even without a postgraduate degree, at the age of thirty -four he became dean of the Faculty of Arts and Science at Harvard University. In 1961, President Kennedy appointed Bundy to be Special Assistant to the President for National Security - a position he held for five years under both Kennedy and Johnson. Those significant years saw the Bay of Pigs invasion, the Cuban Missile Crisis, and the beginnings of the Vietnam War.
When Bundy arrived at the Foundation, he initiated a restructuring that modeled government departments rather than the academic ones President Henry Heald had established in the 1950s. At the same time, he had to contend with serious financial constraints due to Ford's overspending in the prior periods and to economic downturns in the global economy. The Board of Trustees mandated an annual spending of over $100 million.
These economic constraints meant that Foundation programs had to be more selective across the range of its programs. Nonetheless, international activities remained prominent with the new president and trustees. President Bundy and key trustees such Eugene Black (1960-1968, former head of the World Bank) and Robert S. McNamara (1968-1986, former U.S. Secretary of Defense and then head of the World Bank, 1968-1981) reflected a commitment to the international activities. Bundy also added to the board in 1972 the first trustee from a developing country, the Indonesian activist and scholar, Dr. Soedjakmoto, the former Ambassador to the United States from his country and then Special Adviser on Social and Cultural Affairs to the Chairman of Indonesia's National Development Planning Agency.
To create economies of scale, Bundy unified US-based international and overseas activities under one division: the International Division (using the name for the first time). That division comprised Resources for Development (area studies, languages, and exchanges), Population, International Relations, Planning and Evaluation, and the country programs. David Bell, an economist and the first administrator of the US Agency for International Development (1962-1966), was named vice president and served in that capacity until the end of Bundy presidency.
In 1966, Bundy terminated the long-standing internationally oriented but domestically based International Training and Research Program. Several large domestic programs -- including support of centers of international studies - were phased out in the 1970s. Instead, Ford launched under its international affairs efforts a focused but robust program in security and arms control. Over Bundy's tenure, the overseas offices were reduced from twenty in 1966 to twelve in 1979, when he retired.
The Foundation increasingly turned its attention to different set of international issues including human rights and working in repressive societies, such as South Africa. The military coups in Latin America during the late 1960s and early 1970s led the Foundation to initiate in 1976 a human rights program housed in Vice President Bell's office.
In 1979, Franklin Thomas was named president of the Ford Foundation (1979-1996). In contrast to Bundy's international and defense policy background, Franklin Thomas brought to the Ford Foundation his experience in law, housing, and community development. Prior to joining the Foundation, Thomas, a lawyer, was a Foundation trustee. He chaired the Rockefeller Foundation-funded Study Commission on U.S. Policy towards South Africa and led the Ford-funded Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation in New York from its beginning in 1966 until he left in 1979. Earlier, he had been deputy police commissioner of NYC.
In the first decade of Thomas' tenure, the international work was still framed using the post-war East-West dichotomy. Several trustees brought to the board active engagement in international issues: Donald F. McHenry (trustee over the period 1981-1993) had served as ambassador to the U.N. and was active in the anti-apartheid movement; and General Olusegun Obasanjo (trustee over the period 1987-1999) had been Nigerian head of state from 1976-1979, and was then president of the African leadership Forum. Along with McNamara and Soedjakmoto, Rodrigo Botero, an internationally renowned economist from Colombia and former Colombian Minister of Finance and Credit from 1974 to1976, remained on the board over the period 1978-1989.
During the early years of the Thomas presidency, the scope and strategies of the Foundation's activities were also influenced by economic and global pressures, leading to reduced assets and further financial stringencies. Thomas' board-mandated reductions resulted, for example, the firing of twenty senior staff at the same time. To achieve more effective and efficient programs, Thomas had a vision of Ford as one foundation, linking the domestic and overseas activities under new program themes: Urban Poverty, Rural Poverty and Resources, Human Rights and Social Justice, Governance and Public Policy, Education and Culture, and International Affairs.